So in this first case, we have three columns, student name, teacher name, and
في هذه الحالة الأولى، لدينا ثلاثة أعمدة وهي "اسم الطالب" و"اسم المُعلم"
the student's grade.
و"درجة الطالب".
One of the rules for normalization is that we have to have a unique key,
تتمثل إحدى قواعد التسوية في ضرورة أن يكون لدينا مفتاحًا فريدًا،
that says what each row is about, but names aren't unique.
والذي يوضح ما يتعلق به كل صف، غير أن الأسماء ليست فريدة.
If we have two students named Jake Smith, or Pavel Ivanov, or
إذا كان لدينا طالبيْن اسمهما جاك سميث أو بافل إيفانوف
something else, this isn't going to do very well.
أو أي شيء آخر، فلن يفي ذلك بالغرض جيدًا.
Also, if a student is taking two courses taught by the same teacher like,
أيضًا، إذا كان طالب يتلقى دورتين تدريبِيّتيْن يُدرِّس خلالهما المعلم نفسه مثل،
maybe a CS and a math course.
قد تكون دورة تدريبية في علم الحاسوب وأخرى في الرياضيات.
We'll have problems there, too.
ستكون لدينا مشكلة عندئذٍ، أيضًا.
So this is not normalized.
لذلك فإن ذلك غير متساوٍ.
Over here, we also have a single table.
هنا، يتوفر لدينا جدول واحد كذلك.
Here we've given each student a unique id number.
وورد لدينا هنا ضمن المعطيات أن كل طالب له رقم هوية فريد.
And we're also using a unique id for
ونستخدم كذلك معرِّف الهوية
courses, instead of just the teacher's name.
في الدورات التدريبية، بدلًا من اسم المُعلم فحسب.
But, we're storing facts that don't have to do with each other in the same table.
لكننا نقوم بتخزين الحقائق التي يجب عدم تنفيذها مع بعضها في الجدول نفسه.
Like student 23 is always Jake Smith, regardless of what course he's taking.
مثل الطالب 23 فإنه جاك سميث دائمًا، بصرف النظر عن الدورة التدريبية التي يدرس بها.
This really ought to be split into two tables, so this is also not normalized.
ويجب أن ينقسم هذا إلى جدوليْن، لذلك فإن هذا غير متساوٍ كذلك.
And splitting it into two tables,
وتقسيمه إلى جدولين،
is exactly what we've done in this third group.
هو ما فعلناه بهذه المجموعة الثالثة بالضبط.
One table that gives the relationship between each student id and their name.
يوضح أحد الجدولين العلاقة بين كل معرف هوية طالب واسمه.
And the other gives the grade for each course they take.
ويوضح الآخر مرحلة كل دورة تدريبية يدرس بها الطالب.
If all we know is a student's name,
إذا كنا لا نعلم إلا اسم الطالب،
we can join this against that to find their courses.
فيمكننا ربط هذا مقابل ذلك للتعرف على دوراتهم التدريبية.
But, if there are two students with the same name, we will get both.
لكن، إذا كان هناك طالبين بنفس الاسم، فسنحصل على كليهما.
Nonetheless, this is normalized.
مع ذلك، فإن هذا يُعد متساويًا.
And the fourth group, the only difference between this one and
والمجموعة الرابعة، الفرق الوحيد بين هذا
that one, is that here, we're also keeping track of students' birth dates.
وذاك، ها هو، أننا نتتبع تواريخ ميلاد الطلاب أيضًا.
But a person only has one birth date.
لكن لكل شخص تاريخ ميلاد واحد.
And the birth date, doesn't have anything to do with their grades.
وتاريخ الميلاد، ليس له أي تأثير على درجاتهم.
So adding this column to this table,
لذلك فإن إضافة هذا العمود إلى هذا الجدول،
doesn't make this any less normalized than this one.
لا يجعل هذا أقل من ذلك من حيث التسوية.
So this and this, are both normalized.
لذا فإن هذا وذاك، كلاهما متساويين.